<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry revision="1.1.7">
    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>xvidcap</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
        <refmiscinfo>May 2008</refmiscinfo>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv id='name'>
        <refname>XVidCap</refname>
        <refpurpose>Record X11 screen portions to video</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <!-- body begins here -->
    <refsynopsisdiv id='synopsis'>
        <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>xvidcap</command>    
            <arg choice='opt'>-v</arg>

            <arg choice='opt'><arg choice='plain'>--mf</arg>|<arg choice='plain'>--sf</arg></arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--file <replaceable>file name pattern</replaceable><arg choice="plain">|-</arg></arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--fps <replaceable>frames per second</replaceable></arg>

            <arg choice='opt'>--cap_geometry <replaceable>geometry</replaceable></arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--rescale <replaceable>size percentage</replaceable></arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--quality <replaceable>quality percentage</replaceable></arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--source <arg choice="plain">x11|shm<!-- |v4l --></arg></arg>

            <arg choice='opt'>--time <replaceable>maximum duration in seconds</replaceable></arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--frames <replaceable>maximum frames</replaceable></arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--start_no <replaceable>initial frame number</replaceable></arg>

            <arg choice='opt'>--continue <arg choice="plain">yes|no</arg></arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--gui <arg choice="plain">yes|no</arg></arg>

            <arg choice='opt'>--auto</arg>

            <arg choice='opt'>--codec <replaceable>video codec</replaceable></arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--codec-help</arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--format <replaceable>output file format</replaceable></arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--format-help</arg>

            <arg choice='opt'>--audio <arg choice="plain">yes|no</arg></arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--aucodec <replaceable>audio codec</replaceable></arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--aucodec-help</arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--audio_in <replaceable>audio capture device</replaceable><arg choice="plain">|-</arg></arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--audio_bits <replaceable>audio bit rate</replaceable></arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--audio_rate <replaceable>audio sample rate</replaceable></arg>
            <arg choice='opt'>--audio_channels <replaceable>audio channels</replaceable></arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
    </refsynopsisdiv>


    <refsect1 id='intro'><title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            <application>xvidcap</application> is a tool that captures movement on a selected area of an X11
            screen to files. It can operate in two distinct modes: (1) <emphasis>single-frame</emphasis>
            capture or (2) <emphasis>multi-frame</emphasis> capture. In single-frame capture mode 
            <application>xvidcap</application> takes a configurable number of screenshots per second and 
            saves them to individual files. In multi-frame capture mode <application>xvidcap</application> 
            also takes a number of screenshots per second, but encodes them to a single video in real time. 
            Audio capture is only available with multi-frame formats.
        </para>
        <para>
            Recording in single-frame capture mode may be more convenient if you wish to preprocess the 
            images before encoding, or if you need other video codecs <application>xvidcap</application> 
            does not support. Individual images can later be encoded with tools like ffmpeg, mencoder, 
            or transcode.
        </para>
        <para>
            For help, feature requests, or bug-reports please turn to http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/xvidcap/
        </para>
    </refsect1>

    <refsect1 id='options'><title>Options</title>

        <para>
            This program follows the usual GNU command line syntax, 
            with long options starting with two dashes (<literal>--</literal>).  
            A summary of options is included below.
        </para> 
        <variablelist remap='IP'>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>-v</option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Runs <application>xvidcap</application> in verbose mode. This will provide more information about
                        user settings, input and output codecs, performance and so forth. Messages
                        like <quote>"missing XX milli secs .."</quote> while capturing mean you are missing 
                        frames due to lack of ressources (dropped frames). This results in a video 
                        that will play back too quickly. Note though, that verbose mode slows down 
                        <application>xvidcap</application> and may actually be <emphasis>causing</emphasis> frame drops. Try running without 
                        verbose mode and watch the frame drop monitor.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--mf</option> | <option>--sf</option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <application>xvidcap</application> tries to be smart about what capture mode you want. If you 
                        specify <literal>--file test.avi</literal> <application>xvidcap</application> will assume you want multi-frame capture.
                        You can explicitly specify capture mode on the command line with this
                        switch. If, for example, you have your settings properly configured and
                        saved with multi-frame capture as the default mode, calling <literal>xvidcap --sf</literal>
                        will start <application>xvidcap</application> in single-frame capture mode with all stored settings. The
                        default is multi-frame capture.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--file <replaceable>file name pattern</replaceable></option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        File name or pattern to use for saving the captured frames. A file name
                        pattern contains printf()-like formatting (ref. <literal>man printf</literal>) 
                        information to make the file name incrementable, e.g. <literal>--file out-%02d.xwd</literal>. 
                        This is necessary for single-frame capture. <application>xvidcap</application> will 
                        replace the first printf() format string with the number of the frame currently captured. 
                        Thus, in the example given, it will write to files <filename>out-00.xwd</filename>, 
                        <filename>out-01.xwd</filename>, <filename>out-02.xwd</filename>,
                        etc. The frame number to start with can be specified with <literal>--start_no</literal>,
                        see above.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Multi-frame capture does not need a file pattern. If you specify one
                        nonetheless like <literal>--file mymovie-%d.mpeg</literal> for example, <application>xvidcap</application>
                        will replace the format string with the number of the current recording session 
                        (always starting the count from zero). This will enable you to manually in-/decrement that
                        number, or use the autocontinue feature (ref. <literal>--continue</literal> below) effectively
                        creating a series of video files.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--fps <replaceable>frames per second</replaceable></option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Specifies the number of frames to be captured per second. This parameter 
                        accepts floating point values, which allows for very low capture rates like
                        e.g. <literal>--fps 0.5</literal> to record one frame every 2 seconds. This is only possible
                        in single-frame mode. Codecs used for multi-frame modes usually only
                        accept certain frame rates as valid. Note that fractional frame rates for 
                        codecs like MPEG1 which only accept very specific fractions are disabled 
                        in this version due to an inconsistency with fractional timing between 
                        <application>xvidcap</application> and libavcodec. Only integer frames rates will be accepted here.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--cap_geometry <replaceable>geometry</replaceable></option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Specify the geometry as for e. g. <application>xterm</application>, i. e. like this:
                        <replaceable>width</replaceable>x<replaceable>height</replaceable>+<replaceable>x-position</replaceable>+<replaceable>y-position</replaceable>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        This overrides the default width and height of the capture frame. Use the picker
                        button of the GUI rather than this command line option to adjust the frame size to a 
                        given window. Capture sizes below 20 x 20 don't seem to work well with 
                        most multi-frame capture codecs.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--rescale <replaceable>size percentage</replaceable></option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Rescale the output to a percentage of the original input. A value of <literal>25</literal>, e. g.
                        makes the output size be 25 percent of the original input area. Rescaling does not work with XWD
			output.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--quality <replaceable>quality percentage</replaceable></option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Specify a value between <literal>0</literal> and <literal>100</literal> to define the quality encoding. The 
                        default value is <literal>90</literal>. Note that the effect of a value below <literal>100</literal> has changed in version
			1.1.5.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--source </option>x11|shm<!-- |v4l --></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Enable or disable the usage of the X11 shared memory extension. For shared 
                        memory support both client and server have to run on the same host. If shared
                        memory support is available, <application>xvidcap</application> will use it by default. If your X server and
                        client do not run on the same machine, you need to disable it by passing <literal>--source x11</literal>.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--time <replaceable>maximum duration in seconds</replaceable></option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Specifies the maximum time to capture, a value of <literal>0</literal> will cause <application>xvidcap</application> to capture until 
                        stopped interactively. For any other value any recording session will
                        stop automatically after the specified number of seconds. This parameter 
                        conflicts with <literal>--frames</literal> (see below). If both are given <application>xvidcap</application> will stop capturing
                        when either applies. The program accepts floating point values, e.g. <literal>2.5</literal>.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--frames <replaceable>maximum frames</replaceable></option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Stops capturing after the specified number of frames are captured. If <literal>0</literal>
                        xvidcap will capture until stopped interactively, ref. <literal>--time</literal> above.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--start_no <replaceable>initial frame number</replaceable></option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Defines the start number which should be used for numbering files. The default 
                        value is <literal>0</literal>.This parameter is used for single-frame capture only.
                        The numbering of movie files for <literal>--continue</literal> always starts at zero.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--continue </option>yes|no</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        When multi-frame capture is selected, maximum recording time or frames are
                        specified, and the output filename is incrementable (see <literal>--file</literal> below),
                        <application>xvidcap</application> can automatically continue to capture to a new file when one 
                        exceeds the maximum recording time or number of frames. This will change
                        the behaviour of <literal>--time</literal> and <literal>--frames</literal> because recording will not stop
                        at the specified limits, but rather start a new video file. The feature is 
                        esp. useful if you want to automatically split your recording into chunks of
                        e. g. five minutes. If no argument <literal>--continue</literal> is given, <application>xvidcap</application> defaults to <literal>no</literal>.
                        Because single-frame capture needs an incrementable filename to count the
                        individual frames, this feature is disabled for single-frame capture. 
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--gui </option>yes|no</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Start <application>xvidcap</application> with or without control GUI overriding what's in the
                        preferences file. Running without GUI will automatically start a single
                        capture session. It can be stopped by either specifying one of <literal>--time</literal> or
                        <literal>--frames</literal>, or by hitting CTRL-C.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--auto</option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <application>xvidcap</application> supports automatic detection of parameters for
                        output format, video- and audio codec. If any of those settings are saved as fixed
                        values in the stored preferences, they can be overriden by specifying the parameter
                        <literal>auto</literal> to any of the arguments <literal>--format</literal>, <literal>--codec</literal>,
                        or <literal>--aucodec</literal>. This argument is a shorthand for setting all three to
                        automatic detection.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--codec <replaceable>video codec</replaceable></option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Override preferences and automatic codec selection with the explicitly
                        specified codec.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--codec-help</option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        List valid codecs.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--format <replaceable>output file format</replaceable></option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Override preferences and automatic format selection with the explicitly
                        specified file format.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--format-help</option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        List valid file formats.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </refsect1>
        
    <refsect1 id='audio_options'><title>Audio Options</title>

        <para>
            The following options relate to audio capture which is available with
            multi-frame output formats only. There audio streams can either be captured 
            from a compatible audio device (e.g. <filename>/dev/dsp</filename>) or from 
            STDIN (ref. <literal>--audio_in</literal> below).
        </para> 
        
        <variablelist remap="IP">    
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--audio </option>yes|no</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Enable or disable audio capture using default parameters or those saved to the
                        preferences file. If supported this is enabled by default for multi-frame capture.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--aucodec <replaceable>audio codec</replaceable></option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Override preferences and automatic codec selection with the explicitly
                        specified audio codec.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--aucodec-help</option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        List valid audio codecs.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--audio_in <replaceable>audio capture device</replaceable>|-</option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Capture audio from the specified device or from stdin. The latter allows
                        for dubbing a captured video using a command line like the following. The 
                        default is <filename>/dev/dsp</filename>.
                    </para> 
                    <para>
                        <command>cat some.mp3 | xvidcap --audio_in -</command>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--audio_bits <replaceable>audio bit rate</replaceable></option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Set the desired bit rate. The default is <literal>64000</literal> bit. Note that when using
                        STDIN input the input file will be resampled as needed.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--audio_rate <replaceable>audio sample rate</replaceable></option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Set the desired sample rate. The default is <literal>44100</literal> Hz. Note that when using
                        STDIN input the input file will be resampled as needed.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--audio_channels <replaceable>audio channels</replaceable></option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Set the desired number of channels. The default is <literal>2</literal> for stereo. Any value
                        above <literal>2</literal> is probably only useful with STDIN input and a 5-channel AC audio
                        input file or very good and rare recording equipment.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </refsect1>

    <refsect1 id='author'><title>Authors</title>
        <para>
            <application>xvidcap</application> was written by Rasca Gmelch and Karl H. Beckers.
        </para>
        <para>
            This manual page was written by Karl H. Beckers <email>karl.h.beckers@gmx.net</email> for 
            the <application>xvidcap</application> project.
        </para>
        <para>
            This translation was done by TRANSLATOR-CREDITS HERE!!!
        </para>
        <para>
            Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under 
            the terms of the GNU Free Documentation 
            License, Version 1.1 or any later version published by the Free 
            Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover 
            Texts and no Back-Cover Texts.
        </para> 
    </refsect1>
</refentry>

