<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry revision="1.1.7">
    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>xvidcap-dbus-client</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
        <refmiscinfo>May 2008</refmiscinfo>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv id='name'>
        <refname>XVidCap D-BUS Client</refname>
        <refpurpose>Remote Control Utility for XVidCap</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <!-- body begins here -->
    <refsynopsisdiv id='synopsis'>
        <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>xvidcap-dbus-client</command>    
            <arg choice='opt'>--action <arg choice="plain">start|stop|pause</arg></arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
    </refsynopsisdiv>


    <refsect1 id='intro'><title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            <application>xvidcap-dbus-client</application> is a small utility to allow for manipulating an
	    xvidcap capture session from outside xvidcap. Its main purpose is to be used from the command
	    line or key bindings.
        </para>
        <para>
	    For inter process communication this utility uses D-BUS. If xvidcap is not running when this
	    program is invoked to trigger an action, xvidcap is started through D-BUS activation. 
            For help, feature requests, or bug-reports please turn to http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/xvidcap/
        </para>
    </refsect1>

    <refsect1 id='options'><title>Options</title>

        <para>
            This program follows the usual GNU command line syntax, 
            with long options starting with two dashes (<literal>--</literal>).  
            A summary of options is included below.
        </para> 
        <variablelist remap='IP'>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><option>--action </option>start|stop|pause</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
			This sends a command to xvidcap to either start or stop a capturing session or
			to pause or resume one. If xvidcap is not running it will be started.
                    </para> 
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </refsect1>
        
    <refsect1 id='author'><title>Authors</title>
        <para>
            <application>xvidcap-dbus-client</application> was written by Karl H. Beckers.
        </para>
        <para>
            This manual page was written by Karl H. Beckers <email>karl.h.beckers@gmx.net</email> for 
            the <application>xvidcap</application> project.
        </para>
        <para>
            This translation was done by TRANSLATOR-CREDITS HERE!!!
        </para>
        <para>
            Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under 
            the terms of the GNU Free Documentation 
            License, Version 1.1 or any later version published by the Free 
            Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover 
            Texts and no Back-Cover Texts.
        </para> 
    </refsect1>
</refentry>

